

Data Science | Intelligence | Analytics | Strategy

Address Melbourne, Australia 3000

Phone +61 434 443 228

E-mail 007.vipul.j@gmail.com

LinkedIn https://www.linkedin.com/in/vipul-jaina3115944/

Data Analytics and business strategy professional with extensive experience supporting Chief Executive and Board of Directors business decisions. Respected for organizational and interpersonal aptitudes, implementation of strategic initiatives, project management and results-focused interactions across organization.

Pursuing Master of Data Science, RMIT University, following an interest in Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence with Full-Time working rights in Australia.

Professional Experience

2018-11 - 2022-

Innovation Lead | Analytics

GoldVIP Technology Solutions Pvt. Ltd., Gurugram

- Developed, maintained and analysed annual project budgets (> \$200,000 pm)
- Developed AI tool reducing decision time to one-tenth and improving 5 times the staff efficiency
- Reduced communication cost by 60%, costing 5% performance, and ensemble model of K-means and random forest
- Implemented LightGBM predictions, ranking and improving user's online performance
- Developed an algorithm to identify bad quality users, improving data quality by 3 times
- Developed user based demand forecasting, enabling improved budget planning for acquisition, retention and resurrection
- Delivered performance reports to senior management and executives, providing customer performance insights

2018-07 - 2018-11

Analytics Specialist | Strategy

GoldVIP Technology Solutions Pvt. Ltd., Gurugram

- Developed an algorithm through analysis of cost spent on social media platforms by demographics, improving LTV by 2 times
- Collaborated in the development of a recommendation system, increasing 60% transaction rate and reducing 80% daily notifications
- Predicted user demand, differentiated by demographics, using time-series analysis and forecasting

2017-10 - 2018-07 Business Improvement Lead | Research and Analytics

GoldVIP Technology Solutions Pvt. Ltd., Gurugram

- Decreased user acquisition cost by 98% via gamification of business processes
- Implemented business strategies in marketing (Golden Ratio), and analytics, increasing 4 times the gross margin

2016-06 - 2017-10

Business Analyst

GoldVIP Technology Solutions Pvt. Ltd., Gurugram

Developed myriad of automated processes, using python scripting, supporting financial reporting, invoice delivery, and efficiency improvement opportunities

2014-10 - 2015-07

Analyst

Axsiom Domains Private Limited, Gurugram

 Developed detailed technical financial models to value potential acquisition targets and acquired domain names, resulting in profit of \$35,000

2013-11 - 2014-05

Analyst | Commodity Markets

Futures First Info Services Pvt. Ltd., Gurugram

Analyzed stock, sector and market for Gold in CME, generating USD \$24,000 in profit; and assessed hourly market conditions to look for hedge and arbitrage opportunities

	Machine Learning: Decision Tree, Random Forest, K-nearest neighbour, K-Means, DBSCAN, K-Modes, LightGBM, LightFM	●●●● Excellent
	Regression Analysis: Linear Regression, Quadratic Regression, Harmonic Regression	Very Good
	Data Pre-Processing: Data summarisation, Data Cleaning, Data Imputation, Data exploration	Excellen
	Time Series Analysis and Forecasting	Excellent
	Statistics: Hypothesis testing like t-test, shapiro-wilk, chi-square	Good
Tools		
	SQL	Very Good
	Python	● ● ● ● ● Excellent
	R	Very Good
	Git/Git-Hub	Very Good
	Hadoop/Spark	Good

Projects

- Built a ranking model using LightGBM, predicting page ranking for an unseen dataset and using common learn-to-rank features
- Estimated a user review score in a recommender system, using various ML algorithms, comparing results through matrix factorization, slopOne and co-clustering
- Modeled and predicted AUD-INR exchange rate, using time-series forecasting models, performing model comparisons through evaluation measures such as ACF/PACD, EACF
- Used linear equations optimizations in python, to handle multi route problems, built Sudoku solver and production chain optimizations

Education

2021-07 -Current

Master of Science: Data Science

 $Royal\ Melbourne\ Institute\ of\ Technology\ -\ Melbourne, Australia$

Currently in third semester with full working rights, CGPA: 3.5/4

2009-07 - 2013-

05

Bachelor of Technology: Engineering Physics

Delhi Technological University - Delhi

CGPA 7/10

Interests

Strategic Games like Chess, LOL, Age of Empires

Shares and Stocks Trading